Finding Aid for Percival C. Lowery papers, 1920-1967
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Percival C. Lowery papers 1920-1967
Lowery, Percival C., 1885-1978.
1 linear feet
0516 Aa 2
Percival C. Lowery graduated from the University of Michigan College of Dental Surgery in 1910. In his private practice, Lowery avidly pursued improvements in the use of new materials and new techniques and shared his research and practice with his colleagues through his writing. Lowery was an expert in the field of maxillofacial prosthodontics and dental esthetics. His papers document his research, his involvement in professional organizations, and his interest in and support of the University of Michigan School of Dentistry.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (donor no. Donor #764 ) was received from the Sindecuse Museum of Dentistry in January 2005.
The collections is open without restriction.
Percival C. Lowery was born on March 26, 1885 in Harbor Beach, Michigan. Graduating in 1910 from the University of Michigan College of Dental Surgery with a D.D.S., he began his practice in Detroit. On June 29, 1912, he married Myrtle Anne King of Detroit. They had one daughter, Marie Elizabeth.
Lowery studied at the university in a time when the dental school was transitioning from teaching only dental technique to a more research-oriented approach to dentistry. His career reflected this shift. Lowery avidly pursued improvements in the use of new materials and new techniques and shared his research and practice with his colleagues. Lowery was an expert in the field of maxillofacial prosthodontics and dental esthetics. During World War I, Lowery served as a member of the 32nd war board of Detroit and chief of dental service attached to the U.S. Army Hospital no. 36, achieving the rank of major.
He served as a lecturer at the University of Michigan Dental School from 1921 to 1924. From 1924 to 1929 he was professor of prosthetic dentistry at the university. The University of Michigan conferred an honorary Master of Science degree upon him in 1940.
He was recognized by the Pierre Fauchard Academy in 1953 for distinguished service to the profession and selected American Dentist of the Year. In addition to the Fauchard Academy, which he led in 1952, Lowery was a member of the American Academy of Denture Prosthetics, the American Dental Association, the Federation Dentaire Internationale, and the International College of Dentists--U.S.A. Section. Lowery also was a member of and served as president of the Michigan Dental Society in 1929.
He died in Detroit on June 17, 1978, at the age of 93 after more than sixty years in the dental profession. He was inducted into the University of Michigan School of Dentistry Hall of Fame in 2003.
The Percival Lowery papers document his research, his involvement in professional organizations, and his interest in and support of the University of Michigan School of Dentistry. The collection includes correspondence with colleagues and friends describing maxillofacial prosthodontics; some of his works on this subject; correspondence, directories, proceedings, and reports from American Dental Association, Michigan Dental Association, the Pierre Fauchard Academy, and the University of Michigan School of Dentistry Class of 1910. The collection (one linear foot) is arranged in four series: Personal, Correspondence, Professional and Personal Organizations, and University of Michigan School of Dentistry.
Subjects:
Prosthodontics.; Maxillofacial prothesis.; American Dental Association. War Service Committee.; Pierre Fauchard Academy.; Michigan Dental Association.; University of Michigan. College of Dental Surgery. Class of 1910.; University of Michigan. School of Dentistry.
- Personal
  The Personal material series (4 folders, 1920-1966) includes certificates Dr. Lowery received during his long career. Also contained in this series are two scrapbooks with notes on his research, as well as newspaper clippings documenting his personal life. Manuscripts and published reprints of his writings are also included in this series.
  - Certificates 1920, 1952, 1954, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea undated (Box 1)
  - Scrapbooks include information on Dr. Lowery's career, research, and private life 1952, undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Writings 1921-1954, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (5 folders, 1924-1967) describes the various professional activities of Lowery. Included in this series are letters discussing his research, his service to the Army after World War I and during World War II, and from friends, colleagues, and former staff members.
  - 1924-1929 undated (Box 1)
  - 1930-1931 (Box 1)
  - 1934-1936 (Box 1)
  - 1938-1945 (Box 1)
  - 1946-1967 (Box 1)
- Professional and Personal Organizations
  The bulk of the collection is the Professional and Personal Organizations series (.5 linear feet, 1926-1960). This series includes correspondence, directories, histories, minutes, proceedings, and reports from professional organizations in which Lowery was active. The best documented are the American Dental Association (ADA) and its War Service Committee. These files describe the problems of insuring that enough dentists were available for servicemen in war service and civilians at home, and that equipment and supplies were on hand for both groups. Lowery was also active in the ADA Research Commission serving on the Advisory Committee on Research in Dental Caries and the Executive Committee. The Pierre Fauchard Academy files include information about his presidency in 1952 and letters of congratulations when he won the Fauchard Award as the outstanding dentist in the United States in 1953.
  - American Academy of Denture Prosthetics 1949-1955 (Box 1)
  - American Board of Prosthodontics 1957 (Box 1)
  - American Dental Association
    - Committee on Dental Preparedness
      - Proceedings 1942 (Box 1)
    - Council on International Relations
      - Directories 1957 (Box 1)
    - Research Commission
      - Advisory Committee on Research in Dental Caries
        - Correspondence 1937-1940 (Box 1)
      - Executive Committee
        - Proceedings 1939 (Box 1)
    - War Service Committee
      - Correspondence 1942-1944, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Proceedings 1943 (Box 1)
      - Reports 1943 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Dental Clinic Club undated (Box 1)
  - Detroit District Dental Society
    - Subcommittee on the Fluoridation of Communal Water Supplies
      - Reports 1950, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Federation Dentaire Internationale
    - Correspondence regarding conference in Zurich, Switzerland 1956 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence regarding conference in Dublin, Ireland 1959 (Box 1)
  - International Association for Dental Research
    - Membership Lists 1956 (Box 1)
  - International College of Dentists--U.S.A. Section 1940-1942, 1956 includes correspondence, history, and roster of organization (Box 1)
  - Marine Historical Society of Detroit 1957 Directory of members (Box 1)
  - Michigan State Dental Society
    - Bulletin Literature Review 1920, undated (Box 1)
    - Membership Lists 1928/29, undated (Box 1)
  - National Advisory Dental Research Council 1949 (Box 1)
  - National Research Council, Division of Medical Sciences
    - Subcommittee on Plastic and Maxillofacial Surgery, Minutes 1940/41 (Box 1)
  - National Society of Denture annual meeting 1926 (Box 1)
  - Office of Scientific Research and Development--Committee on Medical Research 1942 (Box 1)
  - Pierre Fauchard Academy
    - General, includes correspondence 1950-1953 (Box 1)
    - Letters of congratulations on receiving the Fauchard medal 1954 (Box 1)
- University of Michigan School of Dentistry
  The University of Michigan School of Dentistry series (6 folders, 1930-1960) documents Lowery's activities on the 1910 Dental School Reunion Committee. It contains some alumni questionnaires from his classmates as well as class directories and correspondence. Researchers will also find correspondence between University of Michigan President Alexander Ruthven and Lowery regarding the perception of waning alumni support for the School of Dentistry.
  - Correspondence with Alexander Ruthven regarding alumni support 1930-1934 (Box 1)
  - 1910 Dental Class Reunions
    - Thirty Year Reunion 1940 includes alumni questionnaires answered by alumni (Box 1)
    - Forty Year Reunion 1949-1950 includes class directory (Box 1)
    - Forty-fifth Year Reunion 1955 (Box 1)
    - Fifty Year Reunion 1959-1960 (Box 1)
    - Directories undated (Box 1)